{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The maximum desirable limit Bureau of Indian Standards (BIS) of lead in the drinking water is", "opta": "0.05 mg/l", "optb": "0.09 mg/l", "optc": "0.1 mg/l", "optd": "1.0 mg/l", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Zeolite softening process removes", "opta": "only temporary hardness of water", "optb": "only permanent hardness of water", "optc": "both temporary and permanent hardness of water", "optd": "the dissolved gases in permanent hard water", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Conventional tertiary treatment is", "opta": "chemical coagulation and flocculation", "optb": "filtration", "optc": "sedimentation", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum desirable limit (BIS) of total hardness (as CaCo3) in drinking water is", "opta": "600 ppm", "optb": "300 ppm", "optc": "500 ppm", "optd": "1000 ppm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The chemical oxygen demand (COD)measures the", "opta": "amount of oxygen required for growth of microorganisms in water", "optb": "amount of oxygen that would be removed from the water in order to oxidize pollution", "optc": "amount of oxygen required to oxidize the calcium present in waste water", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hardness of water does not", "opta": "have any bad effect in boiler", "optb": "make cooking of foods difficult", "optc": "make it unfit for drinking", "optd": "cause difficulty in the washing of clothes with soaps", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Permanent hard water may be softened by passing it through", "opta": "sodium silicate", "optb": "sodium bicarbonate", "optc": "sodium hexametaphosphate", "optd": "sodium phosphate", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Zeolite used in zeolite softening process for the treatment of hard water gets exhausted after certain time of usage but can be regenerated by flushing it with", "opta": "10% calcium chloride solution", "optb": "10% magnesium sulfate solution", "optc": "10% magnesium chloride solution", "optd": "10% sodium chloride solution", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Temporary hardness of water is caused by the presence of", "opta": "chlorides of calcium and magnesium", "optb": "sulfates of calcium and magnesium", "optc": "bicarbonates of calcium and magnesium", "optd": "carbonates of sodium and potassium", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Secondary treatment uses __________ to consume wastes.", "opta": "micro-organisms", "optb": "chemicals", "optc": "filtration", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Application of quaternary ammonium compounds as sanitizing agents tends to", "opta": "favor gram positive bacteria", "optb": "decrease gram positive bacteria", "optc": "increase the percentage of gram(-)ve rods on utensils", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Permanent hardness of water is caused by the presence of", "opta": "bicarbonates of calcium and magnesium", "optb": "carbonates of sodium and potassium", "optc": "chlorides and sulfates of calcium and magnesium", "optd": "phosphates of sodium and potassium", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to BIS the maximum permissible limit of dissolved solids in drinking water is", "opta": "1000 mg/l", "optb": "500 mg/l", "optc": "2000 mg/l", "optd": "1500 mg/l", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Acid used mostly for removal of milk stone is", "opta": "phosphoric acid", "optb": "nitric acid", "optc": "gluconic acid", "optd": "tartaric acid", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following chemical is sometime added in the process of coagulation and flocculation?", "opta": "Aluminum sulphate", "optb": "Aluminum oxide", "optc": "Calcium chloride", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following physical method is used as germicidal in modern time for the treatment of drinking water?", "opta": "Chlorination", "optb": "Treating with potassium permagnate", "optc": "UV radiation", "optd": "Treating with bleaching powder", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sanitizer used specifically for vitreous enamel are", "opta": "strong alkalis", "optb": "strong acids", "optc": "weak alkali with sodium  silicate", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The common methods used for disinfection in waste water treatment plants are", "opta": "chlorination", "optb": "UV light", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Phenolic solvent", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Inhibitors are used along with sanitizer to", "opta": "improve their action", "optb": "to prevent corrosion", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sanitizers used for rubber made equipments are", "opta": "strong acids", "optb": "strong alkalis", "optc": "combination of both", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following substances are commonly used in a filter?", "opta": "Charcoal", "optb": "Sand", "optc": "Both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Aluminum chloride", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Biological oxidation processes usually referred as biological treatment, are the most common form of", "opta": "primary treatment", "optb": "secondary treatment", "optc": "tertiary treatment", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum permissible limit (BIS) of turbidity in drinking water is", "opta": "5 NTU", "optb": "10 NTU", "optc": "15 NTU", "optd": "20 NTU", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sedimentation is a physical process used in wastewater treatment to", "opta": "remove particles that are less dense than water", "optb": "remove particles that are more dense than water", "optc": "remove the pertinacious material from the water", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ultimate source of water is", "opta": "rivers and lakes", "optb": "dew and forest", "optc": "rain and snow", "optd": "underground and surface", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Permanent hardness of water may be removed by the addition of", "opta": "lime", "optb": "soda ash", "optc": "potassium permagnate", "optd": "sodium bicarbonate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Both temporary and permanent hardness of water can be removed on boiling water with", "opta": "calcium hydroxide", "optb": "sodium carbonate", "optc": "calcium oxide", "optd": "calcium carbonate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lagoons may be characterized as", "opta": "anaerobic", "optb": "facultative", "optc": "aerated", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Temporary hardness of water may be removed by adding", "opta": "calcium hydroxide", "optb": "calcium carbonate", "optc": "calcium chloride", "optd": "sodium bicarbonate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum desirable limit (BIS of mercury in the drinking water is", "opta": "0.05 mg/l", "optb": "0.9 mg/l", "optc": "0.1 mg/l", "optd": "0.001 mg/l", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "From the following sanitizers which one comes under category of surface active agents?", "opta": "Tetra phosphate", "optb": "Teepol", "optc": "Meta phosphate", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The purest form of naturally occurring water is", "opta": "rain water", "optb": "river water", "optc": "pond water", "optd": "well water", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Calgon is used for removal of", "opta": "sodium carbonate", "optb": "permanent hardness of water", "optc": "potassium carbonate", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The water being used in dairy industry should contain not more than", "opta": "5 proteolytic and/or lipolytic organisms per ml", "optb": "10 proteolytic and/or lipolytic organisms per ml", "optc": "15 proteolytic and/or lipolytic organisms per ml", "optd": "20 proteolytic and/or lipolytic organisms/ml", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The activated sludge process consists of returning a portion of the clarifier", "opta": "effluent water entering the reactor", "optb": "influent water coming out of the reactor", "optc": "influent water entering the reactor", "optd": "effluent water coming out of the reactor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The activated sludge process is sometime referred as", "opta": "fluid bed biological oxidation system", "optb": "fixed bed biological oxidation system", "optc": "turning bed biological oxidation system", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BOD stands for", "opta": "biochemical oxygen demand", "optb": "british oxygen demand", "optc": "british oxygen depletion", "optd": "biological oxygen depletion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When temporary hard water is boiled, one of the substances formed is", "opta": "calcium bicarbonate", "optb": "calcium sulfate", "optc": "hydrogen chloride", "optd": "carbon dioxide", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Zeolite softening process removes both temporary and permanent hardness of water. In this process the calcium and magnesium present in water are precipitated as", "opta": "insoluble carbonates", "optb": "insoluble zeolites", "optc": "insoluble chlorides", "optd": "insoluble sulfates", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The methods used for biological treatment are", "opta": "lagoon", "optb": "activated sludge process", "optc": "oxidation ditches", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Both temporary and permanent hardness of water can be removed by", "opta": "boiling", "optb": "distillation", "optc": "filtration", "optd": "decantation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coliform bacteria in water is an indication of the presence of", "opta": "radioactive wastes", "optb": "excess fertilizer", "optc": "decaying animals and plants", "optd": "human feces", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}